Konvitz, Milton R. Papers /4039
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Milton R. Konvitz Papers
1916-1989
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Konvitz, Milton R.
/4039
204.78 cubic feet
204.8 linear ft.
Papers (documents).
3079854
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, May 23, 2014
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, September 21, 2016
Biographical / Historical
March 12, 1908 - September 5, 2003
Milton Konvitz, a Cornell University faculty member and authority on constitutional and labor law, and civil and human rights, died Sept. 5 at the age of 95. Konvitz was a founding faculty member in the School of Industrial and Labor Relations from 1946 until his retirement in 1973. He was also a professor in Cornell's Law School.
Konvitz is perhaps best known for his American Ideals course, which he taught to more than 8,000 students over the course of his career, never giving the same lecture twice. "I saw the U.S. Constitution as it has been interpreted as a magnificent depository of our ideals, both individual and social," he said. His course exposed students to the great intellectual thinkers and philosophers throughout history whose writings had shaped those ideals. They included Sophocles, whose play Antigone is Cornell's New Student Reading Project this year. One student he influenced was U.S. Supreme Court Justice Ruth Bader Ginsburg, Cornell Class of 1954, who considers him a mentor.
At Cornell Konvitz also was a founder of the university's Department of Near Eastern Studies and Program of Jewish Studies. "I felt it was essential for a college interested in the humanities not to leave out Hebrew language and literature," he said. "And the knowledge of Jewish history, which began 4,000 years ago and has contributed to civilization no less than Greek, Roman or English history, is important to today's students -Jewish and non-Jewish." He often hosted students at his Ithaca home and helped start the first Kosher dining option at Cornell, Young Israel House.
In addition, for nearly 30 years he directed the Liberian Codification Project, which drew up the official body of statutory laws that is still in force in the Republic of Liberia today, despite the current political upheaval there. Konvitz also edited the opinions of Liberia's Supreme Court and received the Grand Band of the Order of the Star of Africa, the highest award given to foreigners, as well as an honorary degree from the University of Liberia, one of seven honorary degrees he received in his lifetime.
Active as a scholar and writer until his death, he wrote books and articles on American constitutional law that won him wide recognition and were cited in U.S. Supreme Court opinions. Among his nine books is Fundamental Liberties of a Free People: Religion, Speech, Press, Assembly, which was republished earlier this year with an expanded introduction by him that is strongly critical of the Rehnquist Supreme Court. Other books include A Century of Civil Rights (1983) and Judaism and Human Rights (2nd ed. 2001). He also edited a dozen volumes, including two on American philosopher Ralph Waldo Emerson, whose thinking shaped his views. One Emersonian idea he absorbed was that readers give life to books, which Konvitz recast as follows: "It is in their hearing that students bring life to the words, the thoughts, the teacher."
Konvitz was born in Safed, Palestine (now Israel ), in 1908, the son of a rabbi. He immigrated to the United States in 1915 and became a naturalized citizen in 1926. He received a bachelor's degree in 1929 and a law degree in 1930, both from New York University, and a Ph.D. in philosophy from Cornell in 1933. Before joining Cornell's faculty, he was one of three assistant general counsels to Thurgood Marshall at the NAACP Legal Defense Fund for three years.
He is survived by his wife, Mary, of Oakhurst, N.J.; a brother, Phillip, of Elberon, N.J.; a son and daughter-in-law, Josef and Isa, of Paris, France; and two grandsons, Eli and Ezra. Josef Konvitz, who grew up in Ithaca, is now an official at the Organization for Economic Co-operation and Development.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: /3033: Milton R. Konvitz Liberian Project Files /4039 AV: Milton R. Konvitz American Ideals Lectures Audio-Visual Materials /4039 B: Milton R. Konvitz Additional Papers /4039 L: Milton R. Konvitz Liberian Codification Project /4085: Milton R. Konvitz Additional Papers
Arrangement
Series I: Correspondence
Series II: Subject FIles, 1942-1986
Series III: Academic Files
Sub-Series 1. Correspondence Sub-Series 2. Subject Files Sub-Series 3. Lectures/Notes Sub-Series 4. Course Outlines Sub-Series 5. Student Papers
Konvitz, Milton R. (Milton Ridvas), 1908-2003.; New York State School of Industrial and Labor Relations --Faculty.
3079854
- Series I: Correspondence
  - "A - Correspondence." Miscellaneous correspondence., 1971-1980 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    In a group of pamphlets from James Luther Adams is a copy of a letter from Oliver Wendell Holmes addressed to Judge Wyzanski in response to the latter's request that Holmes summarize his beliefs in the motives of the legal profession (September 9, 1937). Professor Konvitz mentions in a letter to Chimon Abramsky that he no longer subscribes to the New York Review of Books because he "got a little tired of its dogmatic Leftism, and of the control that Noam Chomsky and I.F. Stone seemed to have over who writes what," (November 1, 1974). Konvitz wrote to congratulate the Honorable Shimon Agranat, Chief Justice of the Israeli Supreme Court, on retiring. Konvitz draws a comparison between the Courts of Israel and the United States and compliments Agranat on a significant role in the formation of the Israeli Court (September 20, 1976). In a letter to Professor Sydney E. Ahlstrom, Yale University, Doctor Konvitz requests references to sources which discuss the influence of Emerson on Friedrich W. Nietzsche and mentions Emerson's influence on his own world view (June 2, 1978). Personal letter from Konvitz to Mister Gershon Jacobson and Mister Nissan Gordon regarding Konvitz's reasons for not renewing his subscription to the Algemeine Journal. Doctor Konvitz explains that although he was "brought up" with a respect and even love for Yiddish newspapers, he found the Algemeine to be too narrow, "not Jewish but rabbinical and clerical, and even the rabbinism that it cultivates is limited to that which characterizes a part of Brooklyn and the Lower East Side," (July 5, 1975).
  - A - General., 1946-1980 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    [1946-1955]-1980. Correspondence with Professor Carl A. Auerbach, University of Wisconsin Law School, regarding the selection of texts for undergraduates. Konvitz prefers not to use the same readings twice to keep the course interesting (1950); Regarding Konvitz's text, Fundamental Liberties, Auerbach is in disagreement on some basic issues. Auerbach does not believe "that the clear and present danger is a 'constitutional jewel' if legislation curtailing totalitarian movements is in question." Professor Auerbach directs Konvitz to Auerbach's article, "The Communist Control Act of 1954: A Proposed Legal-Political Theory of Free Speech," which addresses this question. Exchange of letters with Charles Abrams regarding Stuyvesant Town Case (1947); David Selden, in response to Selden's interest in establishing an American Federation of Teachers local at Cornell University with Konvitz's help, Professor Konvitz informs him that the attitude of the Industrial and Labor Relations professors is that they should not become members of any organization identified with either labor or management (1954); With George M. Houser, Executive Director, American Committee on Africa regarding Committee's request that Konvitz sign a position paper on "The United States and South Africa." Konvitz declines because he believes that the statement's contents relating to the war in Vietnam are irrelevant to its purpose and in some instances unjustified although Professor Konvitz opposed the Vietnam War. He would sign the statement on South Africa if it were limited to the topic (1968); with Louis H. Glickman, Western New York State Regional Director, Anti-Defamation League of B'nai B'rith, regarding Konvitz's concern that the Cornell Club of Buffalo no longer meet at the Buffalo Athletic Club because it discriminated against Blacks (1969); routine correspondence. Last few letters in the folder with Avital of the "Hebrew Culture Foundation" - there are several folders on the Foundation also to be found under "H" in another series of this collection.
  - "Personal A-AL.", 1935-1966 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Personal correspondence including letter dated January 1935 from Samuel Alexander on Konvitz's thesis.
  - Agency for International Development. Routine letters, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Academic and Professional Committee on Soviet Jewry.", 1968-1974 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    1968-1969, 1974. Routine from letters, reports, an article, and a pamphlet.
  - "Adams, James Luther.", 1973-1980 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Correspondence with Professor James L. Adams, The Divinity School, Harvard University, in which they discuss their scholarly activities and opinions on religion (particularly Judaism), the first amendment to the constitution, Iran, and the issue of abortion. In this correspondence, Doctor Konvitz recounted the establishment of the magazine Judaism. Konvitz also recounted conversations with Horace Kallen in which Kallen told Konvitz about his relationship with Barrett Wendell (April 7, 1975). Also discussed is Judge Wyzanski and Professor Konvitz's high regard for him as a jurist (December 11, 1974) and Professor Adam's acquaintanceship with the Reverend Jesse Jackson (June 16, 1975)
  - "Administrative Assistant [1960 - ]", 1961-1969 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    1961-1964, 1969. Routine Industrial and Labor Relations personnel and administrative policy matters.
  - "Admission - 1970-1971.", 1969-1974 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    1969-[1970-1974]. Includes letters of recommendation for law schools, graduate schools, and Cornell University.
  - "Advisees - 1960.", 1960-1963 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Includes academic information on Professor Konvitz's freshman advisees.
  - "American Federation of Labor-Congress of Industrial Organizations Labor Law Research Project - Requests for Reports.", 1957-1960 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    [1957-1958]-1960. Letters from several organizations requesting a copy of Konvitz's study of suits for damages by or against unions.
  - Labor Law Research Project (American Federation of Labor-Congress of Industrial Organizations) [Simon Rosenzweig]., 1957 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Correspondence with Mister Simon Rosenzweig, lawyer regarding possibility of Rosenzweig researching questions involved in the law of agency as they may affect unions. Konvitz is responding to the interest of Arthur Goldberg, American Federation of Labor-Congress of Industrial Organizations counsel, in investigating the question as to when a union can be held responsible as a principal. Konvitz is interested in a study of cases under the Norris-LaGuardia Act, the Taft-Hartley Act, comparable state statutes, and the cases involving common law principles (January 15, 1957).
  - "African Studies Association - 1962-71.", 1965-1972 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    1965-[1967-1971]-1972. Includes by-laws, memorandums, resolutions, newsletters, directories, etcetera.
  - Agus, Rabbi Jacob B. (Beth-El Congregation, Baltimore, Maryland)., 1958-1963 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Correspondence regarding Zionism, the World Zionist Organization, the question of aliyah and American Jews and Jewish affairs in Argentina, Brazil, and South America in general, Judaism and its place in the modern world, European anti-Semitism, and other aspects of Jewish intellectual life.
  - Agus, Rabbi Jacob B., 1966-1986 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Correspondence regarding anti-Semitism, Begin's policy regarding Jerusalem (November 3, 1980), women rabbis and other debates within the Rabbinic Assembly, the need for a Black-Jewish dialogue, the nature of conservative Judaism and the changing nature of the movement. Also discussion of Camp David accords.
  - "Albany, New York Miscellaneous" - Routine Correspondence, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Alexander, Yonah., 1972-1980 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    1972-1973, 1975-1978, 1980. Correspondence with Professor Yonah Alexander, State University of New York at Oneonta, regarding programs in Israel and routine professional matters. Alexander works on issues relating to programs for American students in Israel, international terrorism and other international studies.
  - Am - Personal., 1954-1960 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Includes miscellaneous letters, memorandums, reports, publication lists, minutes, etcetera from a variety of organizations. Also included is a copy of the 1908 "Certificate of Incorporation of the American-Palestinian Society" which was signed by Rabbi Joseph Konvitz among others.
  - "American Arbitration Association", 1948-1955 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    1948, [1950-1953], 1955. Includes letters, reports, and pother documents regarding Konvitz's activities and findings as arbitrator in two arbitration cases: United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America, Local 331 versus General Cable Corporation (1953) and Gowanda Leather Workers Union versus Moench Tanning Company (1950).
  - "American Arbitration Association" - Robert G. Bowling - Syracuse, New York., 1953-1963 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    1953, 1958, [1961-1962]-1963. Includes correspondence, awards with related documents regarding arbitration hearings conducted by Doctor Konvitz. Most of the documents regarding United Packinghouse Food and Allied Workers of America, Local 463, American Federation of Labor-Congress of Industrial Organizations versus Breakstone Foods, Division National Dairy Products Corporation.
  - "American Association for Jewish Education - Collection of Contributions.", 1955-1969 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    1955, [1956- 1964]-1969. Includes requests for contributions and lists of contributors sponsored by Konvitz.
  - "American Association for Jewish Education - Israel S. Chipkin.", 1947-1953 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    [1947-1949], 1953. Correspondence with Israel S. Chipkin, Executive Director, American Association for Jewish Education, regarding Association activities and meetings. Chipkin disagrees with Konvitz's article in Commentary which deals with religion in Israel (November 1949). Professor Konvitz explains the intention and meaning of his Chicago address which he believes Chipkin had "mis-read." Konvitz also defends his article in Commentary. Konvitz agrees that every bureau of Jewish education should respect diversities of opinion and that there is no orthodoxy. He explains his tolerance for differences of opinion and his philosophy "is to look for points of agreement rather than for points of difference in my relations to other persons and in my relations to social movements I am not afraid of differences, and I do love similarity, but one does not swallow up the other." He mentions that he was drawn to the Industrial and Labor Relations school "precisely for the reason that our policy here is to find points of agreement between management and labor and in all other social problems with which we are concerned," (May 19). Also included is a document by Konvitz "Quotations from 'Judaism and the Democratic Ideal,'" excerpts from his paper for the main address at the Opening Session of the 1948 American Association for Jewish Education annual Meeting (May 1948). Other routine American Association for Jewish Education matters and personal correspondence with Chipkin.
  - "American Association for Jewish Education" - Commission for the Study of Jewish Education in the United States., 1957-1959 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Includes correspondence with many participants involved in writing "A National Study of Jewish Education in the United States: 1952-1959." Doctor Konvitz was chairman of the Commission for the Study of Jewish Education in the United States. The file also includes the outline, the Interim Report, memorandums, and Committee meeting minutes.
  - "American Association for Jewish Education", 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    1a. Data Collection Forms for American Association for Jewish Education Study of Jewish Education in America. Includes blank copies of the interview and questionnaire forms. 1. Includes proposals, reports, form letters, and constitution and by-laws (December 5, 1964). Also includes reports and minutes of the B'nai B'rith Commission on Adult Jewish Education, of which Konvitz was a member.
  - American Association for Jewish Education - II, 1951-1960 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Includes proposals, reports, minutes, newsletters, and form letters
  - American Association for Jewish Education, 1967-1975 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    1972-, 1967-1974/1975. Includes publications, minutes, form letters, newsletters, budgets, reports, agenda and some routine Association and personal correspondence. Correspondence with Doctor Charles Berlin, Executive Secretary of the Association for Jewish Studies. Correspondence with Robert H. Arnow, President of the American Association for Jewish Education. Konvitz responds to the draft of the agreement between the American Association for Jewish Education and the Department of Education and Culture. Doctor Konvitz suggests that the phraseology of the agreement should be more neutral and avoid such statements as "the morality of Israel in Arab relations;" "the right of Israel to the land." Also, Konvitz does not believe that it is the purpose of the American Association for Jewish Education to contribute to bringing youth and adults to "live in Israel," (November 12, 1971). Konvitz accepts Arnow's invitation to serve as a member of the National Commission to guide and advise the American Association for Jewish Education in the development of policy, program and curriculum materials for Jewish studies in public high schools and colleges (November 1972 [?] and June 1970)
  - American Association for Jewish Education - Aharon Kessler., 1946-1951 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Correspondence with Doctor Aharon Kessler, Director, Community Service and Consultation. American Association for Jewish Education regarding routine Association and personal matters. Konvitz expresses dismay regarding his Chicago address to the American Council for Judaism because he sees few others arguing "for the cause of liberalism and freedom in the state of Israel," (May 5, 1949) and his concern that such a position has made him a target for criticism by some Zionists (March 8, 1949-May 5, 1949)
  - American Association for Jewish Education - Lown, Philip W., President (1955), 1955-1966 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Correspondence with Philip W. Lown, President of Boston Hebrew Teachers College regarding fund raising. Konvitz mentions that he will help the Hebrew University to plan a labor relations department and if he has any time after he will do some work with the Histadrut (May 11, 1961). Konvitz explains the advisability - and urgency - of American Association for Jewish Education interest in and concern with Jewish education in the area of American higher education." Konvitz emphasizes the need for Jewish education on university and college campuses and notes that Hillel directors on American campuses are rabbis and not teachers. Hillel provides educational services only marginally and does not have enough financial support to address students' educational needs. Also, Konvitz stresses the importance of educating non-Jewish students about Judaism and Jews on a level worthy of the respect of university professors and students (January 20, 1956). In a letter to Lown honoring his 65th birthday, Konvitz praises Lown's contribution to the Jewish community (November 12, 1955). Also included are routine personal correspondence, some routine Association correspondence with other American Association of Jewish Education officers and a summary report of the study on "The National Curriculum Institute" (1959).
  - American Association for Jewish Education - Miller, Jacob M., 1948-1953 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    [1948-1950]-1953. Correspondence regarding routine Association finance matters.
  - American Association for Jewish Education - Miscellaneous Personal., 1959-1966 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    1959-[1965-1966]. Doctor Konvitz expresses his interest in continuing to personally solicit membership contributions from his friends (January 17, 1966). Konvitz was unanimously re-elected American Association for Jewish Education Vice President for the year 1960-1961 (June 7, 1960). Also includes some routine association correspondence, minutes, article reprints, form letters, agendas, proposed budget and financial reports.
  - American Association for Jewish Education - Miscellaneous Personal, 1947-1959 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Correspondence on routine Association matters.
  - American Association for Jewish Education - Pilch, Doctor Judah., 1949-1957 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    [1949-1954] 1957. Correspondence with Doctor Judah Pilch regarding routine Association and personal matters. Konvitz suggests that an Association survey be conducted along the lines followed by Myrdal when he planned the American Dilemma: qualified persons should be found to conduct research and prepare memoranda on topics selected by the Association that way stimulating the interest of young scholars in the field of Jewish education and Jewish community life as a by-product of the project (December 7, 1951).
  - American Association for Jewish Education - Pilch, Doctor Judah., 1955-1959 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Correspondence with Doctor Judah Pilch regarding routine Association and personal matters. Doctor Konvitz informs Pilch that he is leaving for Liberia September 9, 1959. The President of Liberia requested that he travel to Liberia to advise him on labor conditions and labor law. He also received encouragement to travel to Liberia from the Ambassador in Washington and the President of the Firestone Plantations (November 26, 1959). Konvitz mentions that he has been meeting daily from 9-4 with a five-man commission from Liberia to confer with them on the Liberian Code. He expects them to stay in Ithaca for at least a month. He mentions that "the work means a great deal to me, and I am anxious that we do for the Liberian Government and people a first-rate job" (August 26 and September 1955)
  - American Association for Jewish Education - Plan and Scope Committee (Judah Pilch) et al., 1953-1954 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Includes correspondence, minutes of various meetings, publications and reports.
  - American Association for Jewish Education., 1947-1957 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    1947-1951, 1953-1955, 1957. Includes minutes, agendas, reports, form letters, releases and programs, American Association for Jewish Education Advisory Committee meeting (November 30, 1955) and Board of Governors meeting November 5-6, 1955.
  - American Association for Jewish Education - Stavitsky, Michael A., 1947-1954 (Box 2, Folder 13)